Finding aid for the Karen Brodkin research files and recorded interviews LSC.1914
UCLA Library Special Collections
Karen Brodkin research files and recorded interviews
circa 1980s-2000s
UCLA Library Special Collections
Brodkin, Karen
Howes, Carollee
LSC.1914
3.25 Linear Feet (5 shoe boxes and 4 document boxes)
Materials on labor, race, gender, the environment and contemporary grass roots social movements in Los Angeles communities. The materials were produced through the academic research of Karen Brodkin, Professor Emeritus in the UCLA Anthropology Department. The collection mainly consists of recorded interviews in a variety of formats. Additionally, the collection includes audiovisual materials as well as documents, photographs, and negatives from research in Los Angeles and surrounding areas.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS DIGITAL/AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: This collection contains both processed and unprocessed digital and audiovisual materials. Digital/audiovisual materials are not currently available for access, unless otherwise noted in a Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note at the file level. All requests to access processed digital or audiovisual materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9970922263606533
Biography/History
Karen Brodkin is Professor Emeritus in the UCLA Anthropology Department. Brodkin recieved her Ph. D. from the University of Michigan in 1971. Her research concentrates on social movements, gender, work and kinship, political economy, as well as race and contemporary North American cultures. Selected works of Brodkin's include Power Politics: Environmentalism in South Los Angeles (2009); Making Democracy Matter: Identity and Activism in Los Angeles (2007); How Jews Became White Folks and What That Says About Race in America(1988), in addition to Caring by the Hour: Women, Work and Organizing at Duke Medical Center (1988) and Sisters and Wives: the Past and Future of Sexual Equality (1979). Brodkin is also the creator of the 1998 documentary video, Let's Own It! The Struggle of the Lincoln Place Tenants Association.
Scope and Content
The collection mainly consists of recorded interviews in a variety of formats. Additionally, the collection includes audiovisual materials as well as documents, photographs, and negatives from research in Los Angeles and surrounding areas. Topics of the material include labor, race, gender, the environment and contemporary grass roots social movements in Los Angeles communities.
Brodkin, Karen; Howes, Carollee
- Digital images and video recordings, Circa early 1990s (Box 1)
  Scope and Content
  Contains "Oakwood: Struggle to Hold On to a Community" on VHS and DVD; "Let's Own It: The Struggle of The Lincoln Tenants Association" and "The Energy Puzzle: One Man's Solution" in VHS format; "Our Lives Are Not For Sale: EJ Victory Against Power Plant in South Gate, CA" on DVD; and a Mini CD labeled "from CBE: yuki@cbecal.org" that contains five image files of CBE assemblies and events.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. To access digital materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
- Interviews from Power Politics: Environmentalism in South Los Angeles on audio cassette tape, 2001 (Box 2)
  Contains interviews with South Gate community members including students, community organizers and activists, and workers from Communities for a Better Environment. Interviewees include Martha Andrade (South Gate community activist), Milton Hernandez (Youth Environmental Justice activist), Raul Morial (South Gate mayor), Rhonda Nitschsky (Downey community activist), Roy Abadi (South Gate community activist), Xochilt Ruvalcaba (South Gate City Councilor) and Yuki Kidokoro (South Gate lead organizer).
  - 2nd Group Interview with Communities for a Better Environment leaders (Alvaro Huerta, Yuki Kidokoro, Angelo Logan), 2001 April 6; yrlsc_1914_002_001; 1 Sound Recordings (1 audiocassette; Duration: 0:59:25) (Box 2, Case 1)
    CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials are available for access. All requests to access digital materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
    Scope and Contents
    Transcribed from container: Side A only. Copy.
- Interviews from Power Politics: Environmentalism in South Los Angeles on audio cassette tape, 2001 (Box 3)
  Contains interviews with South Gate community members including students, community organizers and activists, and workers from Communities for a Better Environment. Interviewees include Abram Ruiz (South Gate High School student), Angelo Logan (Communities for a Better Environment (CBE) organizer), Bahram Fazeli (CBE staff scientist), Celine Leyva, Marina Jimenez (South Gate community activists), Hector de la Torre, Henry Gonzalez (South Gate City Councilors), Leticia Ortiz, Veronica Sanchez (South Gate High School teachers) Jackie Amparo, Jairus Ramos, Geyman Hernandez, Jorge Duenas, and Marco Martinez (South Gate High School students).
- Audio cassette tape recordings of interviews with Venice activists and from Power Politics: Environmentalism in South Los Angeles, 1989-2001 (Box 4)
  Interviewees include Carol Fondiler, Mary Jane, Pearl White, Flora Chavez, Shearwood Flemming and Regina Hyman.
- Audio cassette tape recordings of interviews from Making Democracy Matter: Identity and Activism in Los Angeles and Power Politics: Environmentalism in South Los Angeles, 1999-2001 (Box 5)
  Interviewees include Aisha Livingston, Aquilina Soriano-Verzosa, Douglas Marmol, Eileen Ma, Michelle Mascarenhas, Milton Pascual, Norma Martinez, Quinh Nguyen, Roxane Auer, Liz Sunwoo, and Communities for a Better Environment members.
  - Group Interview with Communities for a Better Environment leaders (Alvaro Huerta, Yuki Kidokoro, Angelo Logan, Milton Hernandez), 2001 March 1; yrlsc_1914_005_001; 1 Sound Recordings (1 audiocassette; Duration: 0:59:25) (Box 5, Case 1)
- Microcassette tape audio recordings of interviews from Making Democracy Matter: Identity and Activism in Los Angeles and Power Politics: Environmentalism in South Los Angeles, 1999-2002 (Box 6)
  Interviewees from Making Democracy Matter include Aisha Livingston, Aquilina Soriano-Verzosa, Douglas Marmol, Eileen Ma, Joann Lo, John Delloro, Michelle Mascarenhas, Milton Pascual, Norma Martinuez, Quinh Nguyen, Roxane Auer, Stephanie Monroe, Tori Kim, and Liz Sunwoo. Interviewees from Power Politics include Angelo Logan, Carlos Porras, Carmen Avalos, Celine Leyva, Hector de la Torre, Henry Gonzales, Jairus Ramos, Leticia Ortiz, Veronica Sanchez, Jorge Duenas, Luis Cabrales, Robert Cabrales, Marco Martinez, Martha Andrade and Raul Morial.
- Venice research files (Box 7)
  Files contain documents, photographs, and negatives from research with various collaborators and research assistants including Bobi Jackson, Venice poet and musician; Quinta Seward, co-researcher on the Oakwood: Struggle to Hold onto a Community video project about Venice's African American community; Rachel Chapman, UCLA anthropology graduate student and Venice activist researcher, and Oakwood researchers Adande Washington and Monica Russel y Rodriquez.
- Lincoln Place Tenant Association and Venice research files (Box 8)
  Files contain documents, photographs, and negatives from research with various collaborators and research assistants including Mary Hardy, collaborator on the Let's Own It! project with the Lincoln Place Tenants Association and Lincoln Place researcher Gail Sansbury.
- Photographs from Lincoln Place Tenant Association project; notes and ephemera from the Power Politics, South Gate, and Common Threads projects (Box 9)